MICHAEL W. KEARNEY, PH.D.

AI & DATA SCIENTIST

mike.wayne.kearney@gmail.com

(816) 447-8650

linkedin.com/mikewk

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Internationally recognized expert in Data Science, Natural Language, and Artificial Intelligence with over seven years of professional experience, strong theoretical and quantitative backgrounds, and a knack for finding and implementing innovative solutions to complex problems.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

SENIOR DATA SCIENTIST

BI Team & Data Labs

Aware

2021-2023

- Built scalable training pipeline and model serving infrastructure for natural language models
- Evaluated, improved, and reported on performance of natural language models
- Developed creative solutions for collecting large data sets for accurately training models
- Create rule books and train labelers & annotators to label data
- Analyze user behaviors and diagnose training and model biases
- Mentored junior team members and interns
- Served as the technical liaison to non-technical community or public audience

ASSISTANT PROFESSOR

School of Journalism & Informatics Institute

University of Missouri

2017-2021

- Developed course curriculum for classes such as Collecting and Analyzing Social Media Data, Social Network Analysis, Introduction to Machine Learning, Emerging Media, Media Theory, and more
- Mentored over 50 graduate students' theses or data science capstones and chaired two computational social science doctoral dissertations
- Developed and researched AI bot detection software for social media analysis
- Served on various university and departmental committees related to data, education, and diversity

INSTRUCTOR/DATA CONSULTANT

Communication & Research Methods Center

University of Kansas

2012-2017

- Conducted data analysis and consulted on interdisciplinary research projects across university system
- Contributed to project automating personalized analytical reports for students in a large school district
- Instructor of record for courses such as public speaking, research methods, and leadership
- Facilitated working groups on data science and machine learning topics

TOOLS

LANGUAGES
SERVICES
DEV-OPS
DEEP LEARNING
MACHINE LEARNING
DATA SCIENCE

Python | R | SQL | Git | JavaScript | Bash | Docker AWS[S3,Sagemaker,ECR,Athena,Redshift] | Google Cloud Azure | Jira | GitHub | Gitlab | Confluence PyTorch | TensorFlow | HuggingFace | Keras XGBoost | FastText | SciKitLearn | TidyModels Polars | Pandas | Numpy | Tidyverse | Data.Table

SKILLS

THEORY	Natural Language Sentiment Toxic Speech Opinion & Topic Mining
PRACTICE	Human Annotation Heuristic & Algorithmic Labeling Sampling & Bias
METHODS	Transformers RNN/CNNs Statistical/Latent/Topic/Networks Models
TEAMWORK	Research Team Experienced Multitasker AGILE Project Philosophy
LEADERSHIP	Project Management Team Supervisor Committee Member & Lead

EDUCATION

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY (PH.D	.) University of Kansas	Lawrence, KS	2017
Communication & Social and	Behavioral Sciences Methodology		
MASTER OF ARTS (M.A.)	University of Kansas	Lawrence, KS	2014
Communication & Social and Behavioral Sciences Methodology			
BACHELOR OF SCIENCE (B.S.)	Missouri State University	Springfield, MO	2012
Socio-Political Communicati	on		

PEER-REVIEWED ARTICLES

PUBLICATIONS (SELECTED)

- Comparative approaches to misinformation, Int. J. Commun.. 2021
- Exploring gender differences on Twitter with NLP, J. Lang. Soc. Psychol.. 2021
- Collecting and analyzing Twitter data, J. Open Source Softw.. 2019
- Analyzing change in network polarization. New Media Soc.. 2019
- Two tests of social displacement through social media use, Inf. Commun. Soc.. 2018
- Interpersonal goals and political uses of Facebook, Commun. Res. Rep.. 2017

POPULAR PRESS ARTICLES

- March Madness office talk on par with Vegas odds, PR Newswire. 2023
- Doubts cast over Elon Musk's Twitter bot claims, BBC News. 2022
- Using data science to uncover mystery author of Times' Op-ed, Rynl. Jrnl. Inst.. 2018
- Trusting News project report, Rynl. Jrnl. Inst.. 2017

OPEN SOURCE SOFTWARE

- rtweet: Collecting Twitter data. 1,100,000 downloads / 491 citations
- tweetbotornot2: Detecting Twitter bots. 100,000 downloads / 27 citations
- textfeatures: Extracts features from text. 43,000 downloads /4 citations